Guide to the Stephen Sylvester Day Collection of Daniel Mulford
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stephen Sylvester Day collection of Daniel Mulford
1790-1812
GEN MSS 509
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.34
(3 boxes)
Contains letters between Mulford and various people, including Samuel Whelpley and Philemon Dickerson; diaries by Mulford documenting his early education, his years at Yale College, and travels shortly after graduation; a list of speaking appointments for Yale University's commencement, 1806; Mulford's certificate of admission to the Georgia bar; and articles of a legal partnership between Thomas E. Lloyd and Mulford. A scrapbook contains personal papers and biographical material.
Day, Stephen Sylvester, 1850-1934
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephen Sylvester Day, 1912.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
DANIEL MULFORD (1781-1811)
Daniel Mulford, son of Jonathan Mulford, Jr. and Deborah Ludlow, was born in New Providence, New Jersey, in 1781. He received his early education at Morristown Academy under Samuel Whelpley, worked briefly as a shopkeeper in New York City, and entered Yale College in 1804. In 1806 Mulford graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree and returned to New Jersey to teach at Morristown. He began studying law but declining health caused him to relocate to a warmer climate. In Savannah he resumed his legal education and was admitted to the Georgia Bar in 1809 despite continued ill-health. Daniel Mulford died of tuberculosis in New Providence, New Jersey, in 1811.
Scope and Contents
The Stephen Sylvester Day Collection of Daniel Mulford consists of letters, diaries, manuscripts, and personal papers which relate to the life of Daniel Mulford. The collection spans the dates 1801-1812 and is arranged in two series.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged in three subseries: Letters from Daniel Mulford, Letters to Daniel Mulford, and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Letters from Daniel Mulford discuss such topics as Mulford's thoughts about Yale, religion, philosophy and his ongoing battle with tuberculosis. Letters to Daniel Mulford chiefly concern news from friends and business associates, including Philemon Dickerson and Thomas Edward Lloyd. Third Party Correspondence consists of a letter regarding Mulford's death (folder 16) as well as two letters from Isreal Russell to Daniel's brother Levi which describe Fourth of July celebrations in New York in 1807 and 1808 (folder 17).
Series II, Personal Papers, is arranged in two subseries: Diaries of Daniel Mulford and Other Papers. Diaries of Daniel Mulford is arranged chronologically. The earliest diary documents his education at Morristown under Samuel Whelpley, his employment in New York City, and his years at Yale (folder 25). The two other diaries document Mulford's travels to New Haven and Georgia in 1808.
Other Papers is also chronologically arranged, and includes the poem "Contentment", possibly by Mulford; a list of speakers for Yale College's 1806 commencement; several documents related to Mulford's legal career; and an undated scrapbook of Mulford's personal papers compiled by Stephen Sylvester Day.
Day, Stephen Sylvester, 1850-1934; Dickerson, Philemon, 1788-1862; Lloyd, Thomas Edward; Mulford, Daniel, 1781-1811; Whelpley, Samuel, 1766-1817
- Correspondence, 1802-12; Series I; 17
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged in three subseries: Letters from Daniel Mulford, Letters to Daniel Mulford, and Third Party Correspondence. Material within each subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - LETTERS FROM DANIEL MULFORD
    - 6 ALS to his sister, Mrs. Betsey Crane, 1806-10 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - ALS to his brother-in-law, John Crane, Salem, North Carolina, 1808 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Autograph draft of a letter, signed, to Thomas Fitch, New Haven, [Conn.], 1805 Jun 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 6 ALS to his brother, Levi Mulford, 1805-10 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - AL, copied and signed, to Samuel Whelpley, 1802 Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - LETTERS TO DANIEL MULFORD
    - Dickerson, Philemon, 1788-1862. ALS; Princeton, N.J., 1804 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Estey, D. Thomas. ALS; Woodbury, N.J., 1806 Jul 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fitch, Thomas. 3 ALS, [1803]-10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gibson, William Miller, 1787-. ALS; New Haven, 1806 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Keyes, John. ALS; Morristown, N.J., 1803 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lloyd, Thomas Edward. ALS; Savannah, Ga. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mills, H. ALS; Eliz. Town, [N.J.], 1809 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Russell, H. P. ALS; Morristown, [N.J.], 1806 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Lavin----, Mary. ALS to [Mrs. Elizabeth Crane], sister to Daniel Mulford; Savannah, 1812 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Russell, Isreal. 2 ALS to Levi Mulford, brother of Daniel Mulford; New York, 1807, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Personal Papers, 1801-11; Series II; 8
  Series II, Personal Papers, is arranged in two subseries: Diaries and Other Papers. Material in both is arranged chronologically. A scrapbook has been placed at the end of the second subseries.
  - DIARIES
    - Manuscript diary, 1801-07
      Typescript synopsis of bound in front of book.
      "Maid of the Village," typescript of Mulford's poem, addressed to his sweetheart, and dated Morristown, N.J., 1810 Sep 21-22, bound at end of volume.
    - "Trip to N[ew] Haven [from Morristown]", 1808 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Dated 1808 Aug 11-Sep 7.
    - Notes on journey [from Morristown, N.J.] to Georgia, 1808 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Dated 1808 Oct 9-Nov 11.
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - "Contentment", 1801 Sep 23 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Manuscript poem, unsigned, possibly by Mulford.
    - List of Yale commencement appointments, 1806 Sep (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Manuscript list of orators, etc., for the Yale commencement. Mulford's name included in the group of "English orators."
    - Certificate of admission to the Georgia Bar, Hancock County, Ga., 1809 Aug 24 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Articles of copartnership between Thomas E. Lloyd and Daniel Mulford. Savannah, Ga., 1810, 1811 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Signed on 1810 Jan 20 and again on 1811 Jan 1.
      First signature witnessed by John F. Haupt.
    - "Miscellaneous Papers [of] Daniel Mulford." Scrapbook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Contains: undated newspaper clipping about Daniel Mulford with a picture of his grave in New Providence, N.J.; "Trip to Boston," manuscript fragment of diary dated 1806 Sep 27-28; ALS from Jeremiah Hole to David Mulford dated 1790 June 28; undated manuscript map of property allotments near St. Mary's, Ga.; inventories of Mulford's property; "Surgeon's Certificate [of Exemption]" for Daniel Mulford dated 1810 April 27; bill from Kollack & Parker dated 1810 Dec 31; and "Settlement with Matthias Meeker," manuscript copy of DM's account with his guardian, dated 1802 Oct 15.
- Oversize, 0.92; (1 box)
  Box 3 contains Oversize material from Series II.
  - Manuscript diary, 1801-1807 (Box 3, Folder 25)